Cool. Hello everyone. Welcome to lecture
two of CME295.
So before we start, I wanted to give you
a heads up about two logistical things.
So the first one is uh with Shervin we
reviewed the recording of lecture one
and we couldn't help but notice that the
audio was suboptimal.
So what we're doing for this lecture is
to have another setup. But then one
issue is my voice will not be you know
propagated in the room. So I guess I
have one question. Can any everyone hear
me very well even from the back? Okay
cool. Great. So that's point number one.
Point number two is about the final
exam. So the final exam right now has a
placeholder dates for Wednesday, I think
December the 10th. But uh just a heads
up that we're trying to see if there's a
way to move that to earlier in the week.
So we'll let you know when that's
finalized, but for now uh this is still
TBD, but we'll make sure to let you
know.
Cool. So with that aside, let's go into
today's topic. But before we do that, as
always, what we will do is we'll just
quickly recap what we saw in the
previous episodes.
So if you remember, lecture one was all
about introducing the concept of self
attention.
And if you remember what self attention
is is that each token is attending to
all other token in the sequence through
this mechanism of attention. So you have
these notations of queries, keys and
values. So here the idea is that the
query is going to ask which other tokens
are most similar to itself by comparing
query and key and then once that's done
uh basically we will be taking the
associated value.
So we saw that the self attention
mechanism can be expressed in with this
formula. So soft max of query *
qranspose over square root of dk * v.
So I hope this formula is familiar for
you. Um so just know that this formula
is highly optimized. You know these are
like big matrix multiplications that our
hardware is uh very um you know capable
of doing is very optimized in doing
that.
And all of that to say that we also
introduced the architecture of the
transformer which you can see on the
right.
So uh here if you remember the
transformer is composed of two main
components. So the encoder on the left
side and the decoder on the right side
and uh the transformer was initially
introduced in the context of machine
translation.
So you can think of the left side as
processing the input text in the source
language say English
and the right side is responsible for
decoding the translation in a target
language let's say in French
and this multi head attention layer is
where the self attention mechanism
happens
and um I remember there was a lot of
questions regarding you know um it's
called multi-head attention layer so
there are several heads what does that
correspond to
so in the transformer paper which is the
attention is unit paper you have this
figure
which actually represents each of these
heads and you can think of each head as
an opportunity for the model to learn
one way of projecting
the input into being a query, a key or a
value.
So just being a bit more clear. So for
instance for the query and the key, so
this is like each heads. So the number
of these little boxes is basically the
number of heads.
And to better visualize and understand
what this means, um
I also wanted to show I guess what is
being shown in the paper which is a way
to interpret what each of these heads
do. So we have this concept called
attention map
which basically
um
tries to represent the value of each of
these query.p product query.
So in this example what we're interested
in is to see which other token is being
most similar to token its
And so what we do is we take a look at
the quantities
the query that is representing it
product all other keys
and we look at what other keys are
leading to a high value of the product
query times key.
And when you do that basically what you
see or what the paper sees is you have
these two words. So application and law
which are highlighted as being you know
with a high attention weight. So
attention weight here being uh the
dotproduct of the query eats and the key
uh you know for each of these tokens.
And I guess there is also a way to
interpret those. And here you can see
that the tokens that are being kind of
highlighted are law and application
which basically makes sense because the
token eats is referring to law.
So basically the model needs to kind of
learn how to associate these words with
what happened before. And it is also
referring to application which is also
another way of kind of explaining why
that is the case. And so here what the
authors chose to do was to show these
values as a function of these different
heads.
So for instance on the left side these
are the kind of intensity for heads for
let's say the first heads and then the
second heads shows that you know the
intensity is very high for law. So
basically long story short these heads
may learn I guess different ways of uh
kind of figuring out what what words
matters. Yeah.
>> Great question. So the question is when
we're doing all these computations, are
they going through different uh
different MLPS? The answer is that we're
going to have different projection
matrices for each of them. And so um you
can think of um so we had this like
detailed example that actually kind of
uh went through that where
each head is going to have its own
projection and in parallel you're going
to have that computation that's going to
happen.
So each head is going to have one result
here that is then going to be
concatenated and then projected once
once again
with the output matrix.
So yeah, long story short, it's highly
parallelized
and uh it's basically just like
projections and like here you have like
some matrix multiplication and softmax.
Does that make sense?
>> Cool.
Any other questions on this?
Cool. So, I guess this is just a way to
illustrate the conversation we had for,
you know, lecture one. I know there was
some questions about about
um these uh attention heads, what they
do. And I guess looking at the attention
maps is one way of making sense of what
they mean.
Cool. With that, I highly recommend that
you read the transformers paper. So,
attention is all you need. So, it's a
very dense paper. It's just a few pages
long. Uh, but I hope that what we you've
seen in lecture one, you'll be able to
digest the content in a way that will
kind of make sense to you.
Cool. So, with that, we're going to
start the actual meat of what we're
going to discuss today.
So surprisingly
this transformer architecture which was
introduced in 2017
is actually an architecture that has
kind of um you know still stayed
relevant along the years and there are
few components that have slightly
changed and we're going to see which
ones they are. So there are like some
slight variations
but overall today's models are we're
going to see all more or less based on
the initial transformer architecture.
So we're going to try to divide the
class in in in two parts. So the first
one is what I'm going to cover which is
what are the parts of the transformer
that are important and that had some
variation. And in the second part,
Shervin is going to talk about um I
guess the nomenclature of today's models
and how they relate to the original
transformer.
Cool.
Okay. So, let's start with the first
important concept that's in this
architecture and this is the position
embedding.
So if you remember here, we're letting
tokens interact with all other tokens in
a direct fashion. So they have direct
links.
But contrary to things like RNNs where
you have a sequential dependency where
you process each token one at a time
here you're basically losing
this idea of a token being processed
before another one. So you kind of lose
this position information.
So as a result of that we need to
somehow
quantify
positions at sorry tokens at each
position and try to inject that
information when the transformer is
processing the the inputs.
So how are we going to do that? So the
original transformer paper authors,
they choose to have a dedicated
embedding. And when I say dedicated,
what that means is each position has one
embedding.
So position one has one embedding,
position two has one embedding, etc.,
etc.
And what they chose to do is
to add that embedding to the input token
embedding.
So for instance, if I say a cute teddy
bear is reading uh which is position
number one will be represented by the
token representing the token A
plus the embedding
representing the first position.
Yeah,
>> it's a great question. So the question
is are the position embeddings learned
or static? Both. Both as in the authors
have tried both
and we're going to see what the second
one is. But I guess I guess here let's
suppose that they are learned. So what
does that mean? So that means that
basically you need to learn embeddings
for each position.
And um the problem with this approach is
that you're very much dependent on what
is in your training set.
So for instance um like here if you have
somehow a text that always has something
that is happening at position number two
your learn embeddings will kind of have
that bias kind of learned. So that's
like one limitation of that.
Second limitation is you can only learn
positions up to the max number of
position that is in your training set.
So let's suppose you train your
transformer on sequences that are up to
let's say I don't know 512 let's say
you can only learn position embeddings
up to that position right
yeah so the question is I guess how do
you parameterize that so I guess what
you do is you have a kind of a
placeholder of a position learnable
position embedding. Let's say between
like position one and 512.
And basically when you do your training,
you're just letting these these weights
be learned through the regular, you
know, gradient descent, all these
things.
So yeah, so this is like the first
method. Uh but as I was mentioning, it
has its limitations.
um because you can only learn embeddings
of positions up to the max position that
is present in the training set. So for
instance, if you have at inference time
a position that is beyond the position
that was uh in the training set, well
you have not learned that. So you need
to find a way to kind of infer the
value. So that's the second limitation.
And uh but yeah, but on the pro side, I
guess you're just letting your model
learn and uh we've seen that the
gradient descent does wonders when it
comes to just, you know, learning from
the data. Um so yeah and for these
reasons these methods
was something that the authors said that
was performing well along with a second
method which is different
which is around
having an arbitrary formula for each
dimension
corresponding to a position embedding.
And we're going to see that now.
So first method was you know you have
one embedding per position and you just
learn that.
Second method is you have one embedding
per position but you're not going to
learn that. you're going to have
something that is predetermined that
you're going to use
and
we're going to see that what the authors
chose was a formulation using s and
cosine. So it can feel kind of weird,
you know, why did they choose this? But
we're going to see why that makes sense.
So the idea here is for a given position
let's say m
have a vector of size d model. So d
needs to match the dimension of your
token embeddings because of course
you're adding them.
And what you're going to do is for every
index you're going to compute the
corresponding value with respect to
these formulas.
So what are these formulas? So it's
basically s of something time m and
we're going to see what that something
something means. And then the second one
is cosine of something* m.
So who remembers trigonometry formulas?
Cool. Everyone.
So before we go into that, let's just
simplify the notations. Let's just
assume that this big quantity that you
saw is actually something like omega. So
let's suppose it's omega as a function
of i * m
and you note omega i as being this you
know quantity. So 10,000 to the^ of
minus 2 i over d model.
Let's suppose you you construct your
embeddings to have this way.
Then
I guess I want us to think about why
that would make sense.
Because if you think about it,
what you want is to represent
positions in a way that reflects the
following facts.
words that are close together are likely
to be more relevant
as opposed to words that are further
together, right? So, if you have two
words that are like just one position
apart versus 10 10,000 position apart,
what you want is that the one that is
one position apart is more similar than
the other one.
So, let's see if the formula makes
sense. So let's suppose you have two
position embeddings. So one at position
m and the other one at position n.
And let's suppose you compute, you know,
all the values from this predetermined
um formula.
Well, it turns out
if you remember your trigonometry
formulas, so cosine of a minus b is
equal to cosine of a cosine of b plus
sin a sin b. Right?
Well, turns out that if you express
cosine of omega i
factor of m minus n,
this is something that you obtain. It's
just like the identity that I mentioned.
Well, it just turns out that this
quantity
is just one component that appears when
you do the dotproduct of these two
position embeddings.
Right?
Because basically here when you do the
dot product of position m and position n
what you do is you take the first
position you multiply them then you plus
the second position you multiply them
etc etc and then you come here it's s of
this time s of this plus cosine of this
time cosine of this right which is just
this quantity.
So at the end of the day what you
realize is that when you perform a
dotproduct of these embeddings
you end up with a sum of cosine
that are a function of the relative
distance between m and n.
Yeah.
What do you mean by pair by the way?
>> Exactly. Yeah. So basically, so the
question is um Yeah. So the closer they
are, the more similar they are. So
that's the intuition that basically this
way are formulating uh the embeddings is
trying to approximate or is trying to
mimic.
So with that you basically obtain a dot
product that is just a function of m and
n the relative distance between them
actually. Um and just as a reminder so
why do I care about the dot products?
It's because if you're remember
in the embedding world when we try to
quantify the similarity between two
embeddings what we do is typically
something that is involving the
dotproduct of these two. So you
typically have the cosine similarity but
cosine similarity is just dotproduct
over the norm of each embedding. So
which is basically a dot product
right? So that's why we care about the
dot product. And here we see great it's
a function of the relative distance
between the two.
So in particular again if you remember
your trigonometry class
cosine of zero is
one
and the higher this number
the lower the value of cosine of this
number. Right? Of course, it's uh
periodic. So, what I'm saying is not
necessarily true. Past 2 pi or sorry uh
pi just goes the other way. But I guess
what I'm trying to say is for m equal to
n
you'll have basically a sum of cosine of
zero
and it is the value at which
this quantity is maximum.
So when m is equal to n this quantity is
maximum which means basically if you're
looking at the position itself it's the
most similar which basically matches our
intuition
and so now when you plot the values of
the embeddings this is what you obtain.
So here in this graph on the yaxis I'm
basically representing all the
embeddings for each of the let's say 50
positions
and on the x-axis it's basically
values along a given vector across
several dimensions of a vector. So if
you take let's say the first row, you're
looking at the first or number zero
position depending on how you index your
vector and you're looking at all the
values of the position zero embedding.
And so you see that uh for low
dimensions
this value kind of goes up and down very
frequently. So it's more high frequency
and when the dimension is high it
basically takes a lot of time for the
value to go up and down. So it's
basically more low frequency.
So this relates to this omega I that I
mentioned this omega I. So omega I
is
very high for low values of I which is
the dimension and is very low for high
values of I.
So this basically just determines how
quickly your cosine and sign basically
vary.
Cool.
So this is what the original authors
have tried and basically what they said
what they noted was that using this
method leads to comparable results
compared to the learned one.
But here we have a big advantage because
it can extend to any sequence length not
just the sequence length that you saw at
training time.
And this is one of the reasons why you
know this may be something that is
preferable.
So yeah this is the intuition and this
is what the authors chose.
Now fast forward to 2025 guess you may
ask me are we still using that?
And the answer is kind of. So we're
still using this idea of we want far I
guess tokens to be less similar than
closer tokens.
But we're not injecting the embedding
like they did. And we're going to see
why.
Because if you remember,
what you care about is determining how
similar tokens are in the self attention
computation.
And where does the self attention
computation happen?
In the attention layer.
But here what what did I say? I said
let's compute these embeddings and let's
add them here.
But actually what we want is to reflect
this similarity in
the attention layer.
Do you have a question? Yeah.
So in this first method, yes. So the
question is is it added to the input
feature? Yes.
Yes, just add. Yeah. Yeah. But the
problem is we mostly want these I guess
intuition to hold true in the
multi head attention layer.
So this is one of the reasons why people
have tried different variations
and in particular
have these position embeddings
intervene directly in the attention
layer as opposed to the input because
basically when you do it at the input
just here fair okay it's going to be
roughly something that is going to go
into this attention layer but it's kind
of indirect
So what we want is to directly
kind of do something about the attention
formula that would I guess reflect the
fact that we want close tokens to be
more similar compared to further tokens.
And the way we do that is if you
remember
the self attention layer is basically
the softmax of q krpose over square root
of d * v.
So what we want is to add a little
something inside that softmax
which is basically where you quantify
how similar a token is to another token.
You want to add a little something
to reflect the fact that some tokens
they're supposed to be more similar
compared to that token compared to other
others.
So there's a a few methods that have
tried
to kind of have some variation of that.
So
for those of us who know like paper T T5
the T5 paper which we're going to see a
little bit later um they have tried
these kind of relative position bias by
learning the bias term which is in the
formula above.
So what they did was
let's suppose you have a given distance
between the positions m and n.
So their idea was let's learn that
let's basically bucketize
all you know m minus n into some buckets
and let's just have the model learn
these quantities that are then going to
be injected in the softmax.
Yeah.
M so question is does that pose a
problem that the the bias is here with
respect to the probability at the end
because it has to sum to one. Well you
can do whatever you want inside the
softmax because the softmax is going to
normalize it anyways.
So you can think of the bias as being
something that is maybe more negative
for things that are far apart compared
to things that are closer together.
So T5 says let's learn them.
We have another method from
um guess this train short Teslong paper
which introduced this method called
alibi. Alibi stands for attention with
linear bias I believe. And what they did
was
say instead of learning those biases,
let's actually have a deterministic
formula which is as a function of the
difference the relative difference
between those two positions
and they said that so they kind of had
some results. So you know all these
papers they always kind of compare based
on one another to kind of see which one
is um is I guess more performant.
But the reality is is that in today's
models
most models actually use another
kind of position embedding methods
and we're going to see it now.
So this method relies on rotating
the query and the key vector
by some angle
and I guess can think of it as you know
you have your query you have your key
let's suppose in the 2D space so what
you're going to do is rotate your query
by some angle that is a function of its
position
and you're going to
rotate the key
vector by some angle that is a function
of its position n
and
I guess how do you do that by the way I
wasn't supposed to show this thing so
let's suppose you have a vector by the
way
and you want to rotate that vector
because I had the answer on the slide
but guess how would you go about this
guess for people who just want to kind
talk about this with intuition.
So, who here has done uh I don't know
rotations in uh in space? Yeah.
Mhm.
Yeah, that's correct. Yeah. M matrix
multiplication. And you're going to use
a quantity that's called rotation
matrix.
And uh the rotation matrix is expressed
as follows. So it's basically a 2x2
matrix in the 2D plane that has co
cosine of this angle minus sign of this
angle s of this angle cosine of this
angle. I'm looking at the time. There's
actually it's quite simple to just show
that it works. Uh but we may run out of
time. Do you want you want me to quickly
show you that it's indeed a way to uh
rotate a vector?
Okay.
So here as a reminder what we're trying
to show is that we can use a matrix
multiplication to rotate a vector in 2D
space.
So let's suppose we have the following
vector that is something that you can
um you can quantify with uh two
dimensions let's say x and y
you can express your vector in 2D space
with this right
but I guess this
if you note are
the norm of the vector
and
phi
the angle respect to the x-axis.
You can also write v
as r
with
vector cos of cosine of phi and sine of
phi,
right?
So if you multiply the rotation matrix
with this V,
what you're going to obtain is some
multiplication of cosine minus s and co
cosine of this and that.
And I will leave this exercise for you.
But you can show that uh rotation
times this v
can be expressed as r
of cosine of theta + v
and sine
of theta + v.
So this is a quick proof. So I'll just
kind of leave you the multiplication of
the rotation matrix and V but you will
obtain these like trigonometric
identities that will have I guess lead
you to this formula. This basically
shows that if you multiply this matrix
and this vector you're basically
rotating the vector by this angle. Yeah.
So question is why do you want to do
this? It's a great question. It's my
next uh slide. So this is just like a
little intro. Um so I guess here just
going back to this methods.
What we want to do is to quantify the
similarity between tokens and have
closed tokens be more similar compared
to tokens that are more a far.
So
the problem that we had with the
previous methods was so in the first
method
this learned embedding you always had
this overfitting issue because basically
when you learn these biases it always
depends on which training set you have.
So maybe your data set in is in a way
that let's say tokens that are close are
kind of similar but in a different way
compared to what you see at inference
time
and this alibi methods
it didn't have that learnable component
but this was quite restrictive because
it's a very simple formula after after
all right just the relative difference
between n and m so I guess people have
tried different ways of coming up with
something that kind of tells you that I
guess an embedding that reflects the
fact that you want further positions to
be less similar than closer ones. So in
this method, we're going back to the s
and cosine world from what the author
had proposed and think about similarity
from the lens of I guess cosine and s
functions.
So this is a little intro
and their method is called ROP. I'm not
sure if you've heard of it. So it stands
for rotary position embeddings
and we're going to see that this method.
So why why do we care about this method?
So this method has two great things.
So the first one is
that if you rotate the query and the
key,
you will end up with a quantity that
will be a function of the relative
distance between the two. That's going
to be very nice. And that's why I I
wrote this thing on the blackboard. Not
sure if you can see by the way, but um
we won't have time to go into the
mathematical detail. But if you want to
just you know express these things at
home uh this is just a foundation.
And so in particular
if you remember your attention formula
so you have you know query times key
transpose.
So if you rotate the query by an angle m
and the key by an angle n,
what you're going to end up is a formula
that has the rotation matrix
of angle theta and I guess n minus m.
And this is great because this is a
function of the relative distance
between these two positions.
Okay, so why do I talk about this in
detail? Well, it turns out that most
models these days, they use rope, which
is why it's important.
And I would say another thing, it's it's
maybe a little bit hard to get the
intuition as to why that works, but
hopefully the explanation that I gave
regarding the, you know, s and cosine at
the very beginning can help you just
build that intuition.
And speaking of that,
it turns out that the upper bound of the
attention weight given by the query and
the key is such that we observe a
long-term decay.
Meaning that as m minus m is large, we
do see the upper bound that gets kind of
smaller and smaller.
Well, you see these little oscillations.
It's not like perfect either, but we do
have some mathematical
uh I guess results as to just the upper
bounds kind of decaying over the long
term.
Cool.
Any questions on this? Yeah.
Yep.
>> Exactly. Yeah. So the question is the
relative distance is captured in the
rotation matrix and yes.
Yes.
Oh yeah.
Ah it's a great question. So question is
what is theta? So theta is actually
fixed. So do you remember this omega
that I talked about here
here?
So it's basically some function of i and
d. I actually kind of uh passed it quite
quickly. But what I showed you is
in the 2D space but here we're in this
dimensional space which is greater than
two. So I kind of glossed it very
quickly but the way you extend this
method is by having this 2D 2D space
kind of by block. But then the theta is
a function of uh typically something
that you fix but a function of I which
is the dimension you know um it's
basically between one and d /2
it's a function of that and it's a
function of uh d as well. So it's
typically you you will see this theta as
being roughly equal to omega I which is
this this one more or less more or less
sorry.
Oh so the question is uh so that it has
the same dimension as the latent
dimension. So well here
you have a product of matrices.
So you need to have like the dimensions
match. So I guess your answer Yeah.
Does that make sense?
I'll take that as a yes. Okay. So I I
spent a bunch of time on this because uh
I think this is actually quite
important. Uh a lot of models use this
and uh yeah, I guess the intuition is
not super obvious. So I hope this was
helpful.
Okay. So this was position embeddings.
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
Oh yeah. So the question is about how do
you obtain this curve? So this is
actually a curve that I believe is shown
mathematically
cuz basically so it's kind of
complicated. We're not going to write
down the formula but if you're
interested so in this paper in the row
farmer paper there's an appendix where
they show mathematically that is upper
bounded by some quantity and this is
what this is what this is showing. Yep.
Great question.
Cool. So position embeddings is one part
of the transformer that has changed a
little bit and we've seen how that
changed and why.
So now we're going to see another
component of the transformer
that has also little bit changed and
that component is the layer
normalization.
So if you remember
the transformer architecture
is composed again of encoder decoder and
then you have the components inside.
So you have these boxes that say add and
norm.
So what do they mean? So basically here
what we do is we take the input as well
as the output of this sub layer.
We add them together
and then we normalize.
So this is a little trick that the
authors do and it is shown in practice
to improve convergence and just make the
convergence be quicker.
So the idea is as follows.
If you have a vector,
sometimes the components of the vector
can be super large, sometimes they can
be super small. The idea here is to kind
of normalize
the components of your vector
within some range, some normalized
range.
So the way you're going to do that is
you're going to take your vector
and then sub subtract it by the mean
computed mean which is basically the sum
of its components
and normalize it by basically its uh
standard deviation.
And what you're going to do is you're
going to learn two quantities.
One gamma which is going to be the
rescaling factor
and then beta which is um another factor
another term as well that you learn.
And you're going to let these two
quantities be learned by your model.
And so in practice as I mentioned so
what this does is it helps with training
stability and with convergence time.
So this was a technique that was used in
the original transformer paper.
Uh I just want to call out that there
has been some changes since then. Um, so
we went from normalizing the input
plus the output of the sub layer
to having a sum of the input
and the sub layer of the normalized
input.
So in other words, what we've done is to
change where the normalization is
located. So here in the the transformer
paper it was what we now call a postnorm
version
and nowadays we use a prenorm version
which basically consists of having the
layer norm right before the vector goes
into the sub layer and sub layer here
can be either the attention layer or the
ffn
but not only that there is also another
change. So nowadays people they do not
use layer norm. They use something else
called RMS norm RMS root mean square
normalization which is basically a
variation of what you've seen before.
So instead of computing this
basically what people do is they just
normalize X by the root mean square of
the
of the components of X and they learn
gamma only gamma
though. So why do they do that?
Basically they show that the convergence
uh properties they're basically
comparable but here you have fewer
parameters to learn. So it's basically
quicker.
Yeah.
Mhm.
Good question. So I guess the question
is what is the intuition behind
normalizing? So the intuition is that if
you look at your model you have several
layers in some layers your model your
vector your activation to be more
precise. So do you know the the vector
that you see that goes from here to here
is basically called the activation.
Sometimes the activation has extreme
values in one part of its components,
sometimes in another part.
And the model is typically having
trouble in learning the weights in each
of these layers if these activations
they vary too much.
So the idea is to bring the values of
the components of the activation to some
range
that is not too you know far off in some
direction.
So in case you're interested there is
this key word internal coariate shift
which is basically the term that is
given to the phenomenon that I'm
describing here. So yeah that's the
intuition.
Yeah.
Oh great great question. So question is
what is the difference between this and
batch normalization? So batch
normalization
is normalization across the other
dimension which is the norm the
dimension of the batch.
So let's suppose you have a bunch of
vectors. What you do is you normalize
each component
with respect to all the other components
for the same dimension but of the other
vectors.
So you can think of it as just another
way of normalizing. Uh but that being
said uh when it comes to these like
transformer-based models typically
people use layer norm probably because
empirically it works better but also
because uh batch norm you you're
basically also dependent on the batch
and it can be it can introduce some I
guess differences between training and
then inference. So that's basically the
reason why.
Cool.
Great. So we've seen position
embeddings, we've seen layer
normalization. So now we're going to see
a third important component of the
transformer, which is the attention.
And in particular, I guess there's
something I've not really emphasized,
but when you do self attention, you're
basically letting every token interact
with all other tokens.
So when you look at, let's say, a matrix
that shows all the interactions.
So you have like n the sequence length
and n the sequence length. You basically
have of n squ complexity,
which is a lot.
especially as n goes longer. So people
have tried to kind of approximate this
you know O of N squ into something that
is a little bit more tractable but does
not
lose the performance.
So there's this paper in 2020 that came
out long former. So what it did was just
try different versions of the attention
by restricting the window at which it
operates. So here, instead of letting
each token interact with everyone, each
token only interacts with its
neighborhoods.
Yep.
Again, a great question. So question is,
do you do that after the uh attention
matrix computation? You mean the
softmax, right? softmax of so you rais a
great point which is if you do the
softmax of everything why why would you
do this so in practice there is a bunch
of implementations that does a clever so
it's called like tiling bunch of clever
operations that do not involve this huge
matrix operation that you see in the
softmax
uh I guess it's like I guess softmax of
q krpose over there. You're not going to
compute the whole thing. We're going to
have a little bit like some cleverness
in how you compute that. Basically,
yes. So, the question is, can it be um
uh something that's compared comparable
to convolutions? And we're going to see
that in a second. But yeah, you have
some uh I guess similarities with the
vision world and we're going to see that
in a second.
Cool. So nowadays
when you have local attention like this,
like this
people use the term sliding window
attention. So when they use that term
they mean this which is basically just
restricting the attention to neighboring
uh tokens
and nowadays what people do is
in some layers they will have local
attention in some others they will have
global attention
and they interle these layers.
So depending on the model they you know
typically try different combinations. So
there's not like a set uh recipe, but
it's typically something that is used
nowadays. So the window here, I mean for
illustrative purposes, uh the window is
super small in my illustration, but um I
guess nowadays with the sequence lengths
that can be very big, you can think of
this window as being of several
thousands.
So So it seems pretty sizable.
And uh just to give you another example.
So back to the convolution um um like
comparison that you mentioned. So um you
have some architectures and here I'm
going to take the example of mistral
that has this sliding window attention
at every layer. But then uh when you
think about it,
the token here can attend up to the
token here, but then the token here can
attend up to the token here, etc., etc.
So, I guess if you think about it, it's
kind of similar to the idea of the
receptive field in computer vision. So,
I'm not sure if you're familiar or kind
of from the comput computer vision
world, but if you are, um, what this
means is
just taking one token and trying to
think what other tokens
has this token effectively interacted
with, which is basically the question
that people also sometimes ask when they
do convolution. they're like okay so
this value what other values did it
actually see
so yeah you can also think it uh this
way
okay so first variation is instead of
doing the full you know n byn attention
people sometimes do local attention
the second variation that is kind of
orthogonal to all of this is to not have
one projection matrix per head
but to share projection matrices across
heads.
So here the idea is you have let's say h
heads. The idea is you're going to have
some number of projection matrices for
the query, but then what you're going to
do is to group the projection matrices
for the key and the value that you're
going to share across several heads.
Now, you may ask, why do you share
projection matrices for the keys and the
values but not for the queries?
Is this a question that you you're
wondering?
Well, here
I guess you know people do things to
just try out if something works or not.
I guess here you can intuitively think
that uh you know the query is basically
wondering if something is similar to
another thing. So I guess you can ask
yourself this question in different
ways. So it may make sense to kind of
keep that diversity. But one of the core
reasons why we choose to group
projection matrices for the keys and the
values and not the query is because
when you decode
you perform a tension between the
current word and all the words before.
So in other words, every time you
generate a new word, you're going to
attend that word to all the words
before.
So the keys and the values, they're
going to come up a lot, right? So every
time you want to decode something, you
need to kind of attend to all other
things again and again. So we're going
to see in I think next lecture that
there's something called the KV cache
which basically saves the values of the
keys and values
and one thing that we want is for that
cache to not become too big.
So if you share projection matrices
across heads just allows you to save a
little bit of space, a little bit of
memory.
That's that's the why.
Does that does that roughly make sense?
Okay, cool. So speaking of that, there
are some variations as to I guess uh
just how many projection matrices to uh
share. So you have the extreme example
where all H heads they all share the
same projection matrices for V and and K
and in that case this method is called
MQA multi-query attention
you have the you know in between case
where you share
G where G is the number of groups G
projection matrices for V and K and then
you have groups of size uh let's say H
over G.
So this one is called group query
attention GQA.
And then you have the case that you are
very familiar with from the transformer
which is every head has its own
um query projection,
key projection and value projection
matrices. And this is the standard multi
heads attention.
Cool. So, I'm going to just take uh like
a pause to see if uh what I mentioned
makes sense. Wanted to soon uh
transition it to Shervin. But before I
do, I just want to make sure that the
way I discussed is kind of making sense
roughly. Yeah.
Mhm.
So the question is do we apply this to
self attention and cross attention? I
don't want to spoil
uh the show. So I'm going to talk about
something later on. But um
where is my trans? So if you take a look
at the transformer architecture,
we're going to see soon that what we
care about most is what is in the
decoder because we actually forgo of the
encoder in nowadays models. We we have
not seen this yet, but I'm just telling
you and so this typically comes into
play for the masked self attention in
the decor.
But this technique can be applied in all
attention layers. But I guess what I'm
telling you is
modern LLMs, they're decoder only models
which basically only have the decoder
part of the transformer.
We're going to see this in a second,
which is the masked self attention. So
I'm not going to say too much because
Shervin is going to cover that, but
yeah, just a quick peak of of what we're
going to see.
Cool. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Great question. So question is when do
you know which one you should use? I
would say the choice is always driven by
a few factors. One is how well it
performs. Second is how how much do you
care about things like latency costs? Um
and so it really depends how big is your
model, how much you want to save on
let's say compute uh like you know how
is your uh input length like for
instance if you have like a shorter
input length. So here what we want to do
is to avoid having to do all these
things for the whole you know O of N squ
uh thing. So I guess all of these come
into play. So I would say it's not
straightforward as to what the answer
should be. But I would say a lot of
recent models they tend to share to
share projection matrices. So typically
I would say GQA is what you would see
but um it's not necessarily the case for
all models.
Cool. We're running out of time so I'm
going to have Shervin here for the
second part. Thank you.
Okay. Great.
Thank you. So we're going to continue uh
this lecture with uh some deeper dive
into the kinds of models that we have in
the transformer landscape. Um and then
we're going to do a deep dive into one
specific architecture that is very
useful for classification settings.
So
so first we're going to come back to the
architecture that we saw together last
time. So this traditional encoder
decoder architecture where you have both
components
and so you have the original transformer
paper from 2017 that had this
architecture but also later on you see
more architectures that built on top of
it. So here we talk about the T5
family of models. So T5 is a paper
that's like so so it's an abbreviation
of like multiple T's. So the first one
is transfer and then it's texttoext
transformers. So this is where the T5
naming comes from and then it's derived
into multiple versions. So the T5 is
like the vanilla paper and then it had
MT5. M stands for multilingual. uh where
um like there was some more work on the
data it was trained on as well as uh
like the vocabulary that it was computed
uh over and then you have a by T5 which
is some sort of tokenizer free method of
all of this where you forgo
the fact of tokenizing and instead of
that you basically operate at the bite
level. So like by is like bytes and
basically you have a vocabulary size
that is much smaller. So instead of
having like a o of 30k
you have two to the power of eight. So
like a bite is eight bits and then you
can represent every character in two
bytes. So that's what they do.
Um okay great. And then one thing I want
to mention regarding the T5 family is
that the objective function changes a
bit with what the original transformer
did. So the original transformer did
next token prediction for the training
task but the T5 family what they did is
that um they operated on the so-called
span corruption task.
So basically you would have your
sentence as an input to the encoder
and instead of putting everything to the
encoder you would leave blanks and this
is what we call you know span corruption
and then the span corruption could be
one or multiple tokens missing.
So if I want to give an example so for
example
my teddy bear is cute and reading. So
you could have my teddy bear span
corrupted and then is reading. So that
could be one potential
um encoder input and then you could have
up to n
uh I mean n is the parameterization of
the number of spans that are corrupted.
So you would have like n such tokens
here and then the t5 family calls them
sentinel tokens. So if you see sentinel
tokens, they represent a span of
corrupted tokens. So you have them here
in the encoder. And then the decodor's
work is to find each of these spans um
in series. So you start with a token
that denotes the first corrupted spam
and then you start the decoding process
until it hits a prediction that predicts
the next uh sentinel token up to the N
plus1 one where um the kind of tokens
that are decoded between two consecutive
Sentinel tokens corresponds to the
corrupted spans that are recovered.
Yeah. So like this parenthesis is
basically a shift from the next token
prediction objective function. Yep.
>> Yeah. So the question is can you
elaborate with the decoding process? So
what you said regarding reconstruction
is exactly right. So you have sent
tokens that denote some missing text. So
what you want to decode is that missing
text. So the decoder output will be
exactly like each span reconstructed.
Yeah. And then if you want to know how
training works, you do a teacher forcing
um mechanism where you like input
everything in the decoder and then try
to reconstruct everything at once. So,
uh,
any other questions?
Great.
Um, and then now we're going to talk
about another class of transformers
where uh, basically you have this
encoder decoder structure where you just
forget about the decoder and then just
deal with the encoder.
So you might tell me okay hey you cannot
do um gener generation with this and
then I would I would respond to you you
know yes that's exactly the points uh so
this encoder and has so it has encoder
representations that can be used for u
like tasks that might be more geared
towards classification so um like
sentiment extraction uh token
classification like all of these things
that used to be done with specific
language models
they can be done with the encoder part
of the transformer and we're going to
dive deeper a bit later into three um
like key encoder only models. So BERS
which is uh like the central one I would
say in this landscape and then two other
architectures distill and Roberta that
are uh investigating on axis of uh
improvement. So it's going to be good to
see.
So okay great and then uh there is one
last class. So as I've just mentioned uh
like today's LLMs they remove the
encoder part al together and then when
you have no encoder you don't have your
encoded embeddings at the ends of your
stacked encoders that could be uh be fed
to the cross attention. So this module
disappears disappears altogether. So
each decoder that is stacked just has
masked self attention and an FFN uh as
part of it. Sorry.
And uh yeah that's basically um you know
something that has uh caught up uh since
then because when you look at the
popularity of each of these models so
you used to have this like transformer-l
like architecture that was popular
towards the beginning where the main
hypothesis was that like the encoder
part is very useful for like getting to
the like decoded representation but as
time went people realized that your
computes budget could be best invested
in the decoder only. uh and then um you
know you had there there has been more
investment into the kind of task that is
I would say easiest to scale up and
generalize next word prediction as
opposed to the task I just mentioned for
T5 which might be uh kind of more
bespoke so you need to like corrupt
things and then you know so it's more
complex whereas like next word
prediction is I would say like the
simplest thing you can do and it showed
uh like it proved to wonders and well
aligns with the task of being a a
helpful kind of chatbot which is like
today's applications mainly
and then the decoder only architectures
so I'm not going to talk about them
today uh but it's going to be the
central part of the next lectures uh
when we're going to talk about LLMs more
and more
okay awesome So now we can dive deep
into you know as promised into encoder
only architectures and with birds.
So first we're going to start by you
know seeing what does BERT mean. So BERT
it's an acronym that denotes birectional
uh encoders representations from
transformers. and we're going to see
together how does each section of this
acronym what does it correspond to. So
let's just start with uh the encoder
part which is like the easiest to to
grasp. So as we said we just drop the
decoder. So like this encoder from
transformer is basically exactly what it
means.
Now on the other part so uh so why do we
talk about birectionality?
So it's a way um so so the paper's
result is kind of remark remarkable
because we are able from a given input
to get um like output representations
that have attended to everything you
know for each token.
And um this is the case because since we
only have the encoder, we have this self
attention layer that truly attends to
every other token.
And this is in contrast with the masked
self attention that you have where we
said that the mask is making the
attention mechanism causal. So every
token can attend to itself and to the
tokens before it. And this is by the way
something that the authors
like discuss a lot in the paper saying
that you know GPT came out GPT they're
not truly birectional and then these
encodings that can be used for
classification task they truly are.
Any questions?
Yep.
Yep, that's right. So, uh the question
is when you don't have the mask, each
token can attend to each other. You
know, that's exactly right. And then the
mask is exactly there to prevent links
from tokens to like those that that kind
of come after them. Yeah.
Okay. Great.
So I just want to put this paper in
context and you know the field of NLP
was booming back then. So you had
another landmark paper that same year
which was called Elmo. So embeddings
from language models and I would say
that the timing of that uh paper was a
bit unfortunate because it truly had new
insights of also building birectional
representations but it just turns out
that it came the same year as a
transformer like as as a kind of
transformer-based like same line of
work. So it got a bit masked by it. So,
Elmo just to give the main lines, it was
based on a birectional
LSTM where you had multiple layers um
you stacked on top of each other and
basically you were able to build a
birectional representation for each word
thanks to this um architecture. And so
why didn't it uh get you know why didn't
it become as popular as BERT? It's
because you had the same downsides as
the previous models where basically it's
hard to scale uh because of this
recurrence.
Um and um you know I think a lot of you
you know when you think about Elmo and
Bert you don't think about these papers
you know at first because they are part
of like their characters in Sesame
Street and you know I grew up in a place
where I I did not know about Sesame
Street. So like for me Elma and Berts is
like a paper names but you know it might
be you know what represents to you um
you know at first so I thought that was
quite funny and then you know
researchers they're generally quite um
you know playful they have u like they
try to fit their acronyms into like
themes. So if you look at paper names
you you'll get um entertained.
Okay great.
So to dive deeper into what I mentioned
to be the goal of encoder only models.
So you have your set of tokens as input
and the goal here is to perform tasks
that might be uh focused on projecting
some representation somewhere. So
typically classification tasks and here
the uh like the way BERT works is very
specific. So you have two kinds of
tokens that you will see uh are kind of
structural here. So you have first this
CLS token which is which stands for
classification
and it's basically a placeholder token
that is put at the beginning of the
sequence that will then uh at the end of
the whole attention and then projection
and you know the whole encoder mechanism
be projected into an embedding that we
can then uh use for classification.
So yeah, CLS is just some kind of
placeholder that will uh carry the
birectional information of your whole
input.
And another uh token that might be you
know useful to see is this SEP token. So
it's like separator. Um and then you
will see uh very soon we're we're going
to see the objective functions that it
operates on. It's uh it aims at
separating uh two sentences.
Uh yeah.
So this is the very high level and then
um so one thing that is very interesting
to see with this model is that you you
have this concept of multi-stage
training. So you don't train the model
you know in one shot. You do it in
multiple stages. So the first stage is
aimed at being aligned with the task of
interest. And uh so this is what we call
pre-training
and this pre-training we will see in
detail is done with two objective
functions that are respectively MLM and
NSP. So MLM stands for masked lang
language model and NSP is the next
sentence prediction.
So masked language model it's a way for
the model to learn the internal
structure of the uh of the inputs and
then NSP it might be um seen as a way to
see like if the ordering of sentences
make sense. So we're going like to go
like a bit deeper into each but it's a
combination of objective function that
the authors
um you know assume to be helpful for
learning like general uh general
embeddings of high quality.
Okay. So the second thing that I want to
mention is that once you have all of
this you have a further stage where you
keep the embeddings that you have
learned and then you attach to it some
other network like typically a linear
projection to then fine-tune
uh what's like the embeddings that you
have learned into some target task. So
this is what we call fine-tuning.
Yep.
So yes, so so the question is um do we
still have just an encoder here? Because
a next sentence prediction is, you know,
could be seen as a decoder task. So it's
actually I'm going to go in detail. The
next sentence prediction task is
actually us putting two sentences one
after the other and predicting whether
they're truly consecutive.
Uh yeah, so it's a classification task.
Yeah, great points and yeah, we're going
to see that in detail very soon.
So before we see that in detail, um I'm
going to discuss the pros and cons uh
that this method usually has. So um
so regarding uh like on the pros side,
like this pre-training um mechanism can
be done on like fairly unlabelled data.
So you still have this like next
sentence prediction task, but this is
something that you control because you
know which sentences follow each other.
So it's something that you kind of you
know you know you know it's kind of
self-s supervised
and the masked language model task.
We're going to see how it um you know
how it consists but um but it's also
something that is unsupervised. So this
is a very interesting way to learn
interesting embeddings out of unlabeled
data. And then uh in practice is that we
see that this unlabeled data leads to
helpful representations being learned
and then you need very little data to
build on top of it. So at the finetuning
stage you just start from these very
nice embeddings that you have learned
and you just have a few weights to tune
and then this usually leads to um
performance that exceeds
state-of-the-art back then
and um and then regarding uh you know
downsides we have uh you know of course
all the text generation uh kind of tasks
that are out of reach because we don't
have a decoder and also we can see this
two-stage process and the fact that we
need to further tune embeddings as
something that that can be you know over
hurdles. So it might be uh you know when
you compare this kind of methodology
with respect to more traditional methods
that can be you know one shot this could
be seen as a downside.
Okay, great. And uh you know I have some
uh you know names regarding uh variants
here. We're going to dive deep into two
of them a bit later on.
Okay. So I want us to focus on the
original transformer and we're going to
go step by step into what happened to it
and then how we get the BERT
architecture.
So this is what we had in the original
transformer paper that we saw last week.
And what BERT did is extract the encoder
part of it and attach basically this new
um objective functions that I just
mentioned alongside some new set of
tricks uh when it comes to representing
uh tokens.
So I think we're going to go uh
you know we're going to go through them
one by one. So first of all one uh
interesting note is that it uses a
specific tokenizer called word piece. So
you can see it as a tokenizer that
learns on your training set based on uh
you know merge rules that maximize the
likelihood. So basically you have some
huge training set and you train a
tokenizer that merges atomic tokens
together to build uh your target
vocabulary
and there's some order of magnitudes I
mentioned of 30k so it's typically you
know uh I think this is the size that
they chose in this paper and in general
um like vocabulary sizes in this sort of
paper are in the order of magnitude of
10 to the^ of four 10 to the^ of
Except for our token free method that we
saw like by T5 which is like this very
restricted set of tokens like two to the
power of eight which is like 256 you
know apart from this specific case you
you always have um kind of this order of
magnitude
and
uh okay and basically we are going to
make use of the tokens that I mentioned
um like at the beginning. So you have
the saleless token that is going to
carry the birectional representation of
all your uh sequence and then you have
SIP tokens to separate the two sentences
towards the next sentence prediction
task
and there is something that I haven't
talked about just yet. Uh so I think
maybe we can talk about it at the time
of the deep dive. So basically in order
so in order to have this like masked
language model task so of course you
need to mask some token. So we're going
to see the technique that is uh
basically applying the sort of mask and
where and at each fre at which frequency
and we're going to see with respect to
the output what is going to be our task
based on the resulting representation.
So I'm just going to like pass quickly
on it here, but we're going to come back
very soon.
Okay, great. Um, so one big piece of
news regarding your input embeddings. So
like what stays the same. So you still
have this huge dictionary lookup of
embeddings for each token that you're
going to learn and you're going to
additively add the positional encoding
that we saw at last lecture um and Afin
talked about earlier in this lecture
which can either be hardcoded or
learned. Uh I think the authors here
just uh use an a hard-coded version
here. Uh but I'm not too sure like but
it's roughly the same performance
usually.
But there is something new.
There is the introduction of a new kind
of encoding called segment encoding that
is going to still be additively added to
tokens
uh with the exception that we just have
two uh two possible encodings there. So
you have segment A that represents the
first sentence and then segment B that
represents the second sentence. And it's
supposed to help with the NSP task to
represent you know what could be
features that can helpfully represent a
sentence that precedes another one. Uh
so at least that was the hypothesis
emitted by the authors. We're going to
see it has been challenged later on but
uh you know this is one of the key
concepts that was introduced here.
Any questions so far?
>> Yep.
Yeah. So great point. So the question is
what does segment encoding like do at
all? So it's basically something that is
learned. So you have two indices like
two basically embeddings that you can
learn. you just additively add them uh
you know segment A for like tokens in in
the first part of the sentence and then
segment B in the second part and you
just learn uh you know you just learn it
with gradient descent so you do nothing
with it
I think there was another question here
that's right so the question is uh is
every token in the same sentence going
to have the same segment encoding the
yes. Yep.
Okay. Awesome. So I'm seeing I might
need to speed up a tiny bit. Um so yeah
the second thing that I want to
highlight here is that we take the
encoder parts of the transformer and uh
you know nothing new here. It's just
like the same. We have self attention
followed by uh this like FFN. Uh so this
is where you're going to get your
birectional uh nature of your encodings.
Um and then basically we're assuming
that training both MLM and NSP on it is
going to help us uh like learn helpful
projection matrices in this encoder that
can be suited for any classification
task.
Okay, great. And then I you know as
promised I talked about you know
detailing more about like what this MLM
task was going to do. So when you uh
look at the input you're going to uh
basically have your input sentence and
replace at random some tokens. uh so it
will be replaced either with the token
mask so it's in 80% of the time in 10%
of the time the tokens selected for this
like MLM uh objective function are not
going to be replaced at all so we just
say you know it's the same token just
predict the same token and then 10% of
the time it's going to be changed to
some random other world uh word so at
the end of it you have this subset of
tokens you're going to perform your MLM
task on. And then this is, you know, how
it's composed.
Uh, okay, great. And so basically the
intuition here is that when you want to
predict what a token is, you need to
know about its context. So you're going
to force the model to learn about what
surrounds it left and right. So kind of
this is the birectional
um, you know, property of this
architecture put into action.
Okay, great. And now we're going to talk
about like the next sentence prediction
task where um basically the process here
is to put is to select two sentences
from a given corpus and then present
them um you know side by side in order
50% of the time and in some random order
the other um kind of part of the time.
And the goal is for some classification
head on top of the CLS token to
determine whether A and B are
consecutive. So that's all it does.
And yeah, so the assumption is that it
also helps uh learn some useful
embeddings.
Okay, great. And uh here I'm going to
present the notation that is used in the
paper. So the paper is something I
recommend reading. It's a very nice
read. Alongside the attention is all you
need. I would say it's like a landmark
paper. I think it has like 170k
citations. Something really impressive.
Um and uh basically what we called N in
the original transformer paper is now
called L. H that was called D model is
the dimension of our embeddings and A is
uh the number of attention heads which
was called a little h. So here I'm just
showing these new notations for
information just to like give you the
mapping but of course together with Afin
we're going to stay consistent with the
original notations we had. So just like
for information
and uh one interesting note is that you
will see that the bird model uh when you
look at some um repository of models
such as hugging face so usually it's
it's given in several versions uh so you
will see sometimes like cased uncased.
Uh so this denotes what kind of
pre-processing was done to the data
whether you only have lower case um
words in there or whether casing
matters. So based on your task of
interest it might be you know one thing
you want to choose from.
Okay, great.
And uh you know I give some orders of
magnitude from the paper on um you know
what values were chosen for uh for for
each of these. So if I remember
correctly I think the original
transformer had like 12 stacked encoders
and decoders. Um yeah so I think it's
like some some numbers here were kind of
taken from there and um yeah so yeah or
order of magnitudes is 100 million
parameters.
Any questions so far?
Okay, great.
Um, and then now we're going to talk
about the fine-tuning stage where the
goal is to basically
take whatever we have learned at
pre-training stage and then freeze those
weights and instead of training again on
the same weights, you have some
classification
linear layer that is put on top of
either the CLS token or on top of tokens
of interest. And you're going to learn
about the linear embeddings there.
You're going to have some classification
task. So you can either you know freeze
all these like pre-trained weights and
just you know train on these small
weights or you can just retrain the
whole thing. I think there's like a
multiple classification schemes and some
of it will be influenced by your
willingness to retrain a lot of the
network and how different the
classification task is with respect to
the original pre-training task.
Um okay great and then just to give some
examples of what could be fine-tuning
tasks for you know tasks of interest you
can have a sentiment extraction where
you build a classification layer on top
of the CLS token and we give some other
um you know example a question answering
where basically you are given some
inputs and the goal of the model is to
detect
beginning and end spans of the response.
So it's basically some objective
function that is at the token level.
Okay, great. So now I propose that we do
some deep dive into one specific uh
example uh you know our favorite
example. Um this teddy bear is so cute.
Let's just see how um BERT works in
practice.
So basically what you would do in an
uncased setting is take the sentence
like pre-process it like just put
everything lower case
then you apply the word piece algorithm
on whatever tokenization mechanism that
your uh like tokenizer has learned. So
for example here you know apparently it
had all these merge rules. So this is
kind of the tokens that appear in the
vocabulary.
And then as I promised, we add the CLS
token at the beginning. And then we add
the SE token. And you also have these
like um you know pads tokens that are
basically
um used to fill out the the sequence
until the end. cuz when you train, you
train by batch and then batches are
composed of matrices that have a fixed
length.
Uh yeah,
so let's just have like this deep dive a
bit the same as uh like what we had in
the transformer uh deep dive last time.
So you have the embeddings that are
learned. So it's like some huge uh
lookup table uh between the index of
each token and a learn representation.
So you add to it the position embedding
of the token and something that's new
here the segment embedding. So exactly
as we said it's an embedding that is
added to each token and the same
embedding is added to the same tokens.
So to all the tokens of the same uh
segment A and then some other embedding
B is added to all the tokens of the
segment B.
Okay, great. So now you have you
similarly as a transformer something
that is position aware and context aware
um so not context aware just yet but uh
segment aware here
uh okay great and uh basically um it's
it goes through this encoder
architecture and then at the end of it
for the case of sentiment extraction we
do not care about the embeddings that
are uh corresponding to each token.
that is not the CLS token because what
we care about is the output embedding of
the CLS token where we plug a linear
layer uh that will learn some uh
classification task.
So any question here?
So, does the fact that we drop all the
output embeddings apart from the CS
token make sense?
Yep.
>> Yes. So the question is uh what does
this uh you know FFN is that right? What
does this FFN correspond to? So
basically you have a map between the
dimension of the output embedding and
your task of interest. So it might be
classification of um you know you know
either either positive or negative. So
you have some hidden layer with some
with some length. So you have like
typically two matrices to learn the
projection from one to that hidden layer
and then the hidden layer to the output
and then you learn these weights in
order to do the classification task
based on the embeddings that it has
learned here.
Yeah, great question. So that was the
question I was waiting for. So the
question is why do we throw away all
these other uh you know output
embeddings so we don't need them need
them here. So we are in a classification
task. we have put as uh convention to
operate on top of some token like the
CLS token and then the magic of this
token is that all these self attention
mechanisms that are in the encoder has
mixed the representation of each of the
other tokens in that representation
such that the output embeddings they are
context aware. So basically it's a it's
an embedding that is geared towards
classification and this is what we say
you know will be what we plug in to that
uh you know linear layer
and um so when I say you know we throw
out all the other embeddings
it's actually something that we do for
the case of classification but if we do
classification at the token level then
each of them may be used so for example
when I said question answering if you
want to detect whether
um you know like a given token is the
beginning of a of an answer uh beginning
of end of an answer. You would typically
have two FFNs that respectively predict
the start and end of the answer and you
would apply it on each of these
embeddings.
Any other questions? Yep.
So the question is what is query key and
value for CLS? So it's going to be the
same process as all the other tokens. So
you learn here a representation for the
embedding for the token CLS.
It gets projected to uh you know query
it gets projected to key it gets
projected to value. it does all its
attention computation and at the end you
get this embedding that is basically um
you know that has intended to all the
other ones. So it's like the answer is
it's the same as for the other tokens.
So yeah, so just treat it as one token,
you know, could be any token and and
it's the same.
Okay, awesome. So I see we have five
more minutes and I'm going to uh you
quickly go through the end of it and um
you know one thing that was great with
birds and it was also you know great
with Elmo is that you have embeddings
that are contextual
um and here uh you can see that it's
very easy to learn any classification
task that you want based on this learn
embeddings. So this is a flexibility
that was greatly appreciated here
and it's widely used in the industry. So
anything that comes with sentiment
detection or like other classification
related tasks, it's very common to use a
BERT like model for it nowadays
and um I'm going to talk a bit about its
limitations now. So um as you see in the
original paper I think the context
length was of size 512. So it was
typically limited in this um kind of
early paper
has mentioned of techniques as to how we
can further grow this context size
without making the complexity go
completely you know basically like high.
uh and then you have some uh
approximation methods where you compute
local attention and so on and then the
use of these tricks helps you grow the
size of the context while staying within
reasonable uh computation requirement
bounds and I'm going to talk about two
other limitations that we're going to
see what other models try to remedy. So
there is one where um you know the
latency could be seen as high. You have
a still 110 million parameters for a
bird base. So it's quite a lot you know
is there a way to make this you know
smaller and faster and then the second
one is basically you have these two
objective functions of MLM and NSP. Are
those two truly helpful? Is there any
way we can simplify the pre-training
process? So we're going to see uh in a
second how.
Um so first regarding this second
limitation that we had this uh basically
um
this basically uh you know sensitivity
to cost. So so who here has heard of
distillation?
Okay great few people. So I just want to
like flash this quote from uh Hinton uh
Vinas and Jeff Dean uh which I think is
very uh informative and kind of it's a
good mindset to have to see that the
distribution that is output by a given
model is actually super helpful to know
what it has learned. So it's the soft
targets contain almost all the
knowledge. So it's like some lecture
from from them that contain this these
quotes and I feel so so basically they
were at the origin of the concept of
distillation later on and you quickly
see in practice that basically learning
the distribution of a model is more
helpful than directly learning the hard
labels.
So you have this concept of teacher and
student models where basically um you
know the goal in distillation is going
to be to map this output distribution of
a smaller model directly to your more
complex model rather than the hard
labels.
And the um you know the objective
function that you use for this to
minimize this is the KL divergence
which basically says in a world that is
described by the teacher the teacher T
how bad is it to model with the student
S. So it basically kind of tries to
assess how close the student
distribution is going to be to the
world's t. And um one interesting note
that you will see here is that you find
the cross entropy loss if your yt
distribution is just a hard label. So if
you have just a one at one position and
then zero everywhere else you have minus
log of you know ys which is very
interesting.
And then when the distilled bear forks
have done so by the way it's a very
clean paper it's like four pages but
super impactful. So it says that you
know if you reduce the number of layers
by two you have a lot of gains and
almost the same performance
uh which is kind of very remarkable and
they basically used distillation as a
way to retain that performance. So this
has been like the key alongside the the
like diminishing the number of layers.
And last I'm going to talk about Roberta
that uh studied the fact that removing
the NSP
um objective function led to no decrease
in performance almost. So they just
dropped it. And they added some tricks
such as um you know dynamically doing
the masking. So for example for a given
piece of text at each epoch so every
time you see the same kind of text you
would change the masking and they also
had some data strategy where they saw
that the model was vastly undertrained.
So they increased the diversity and the
size of the data a lot and they saw that
uh kind of benchmark performance
increased uh quite a bit on the same
benchmarks.
And that's it for today. Thank you
everyone. Have a great weekend.